又有三个人今早跑了
Three more gone this morning.
都是贱民
Outcasts and idiots.
他们都变得躁动不安，在战争结束的时候
They all get restless. With the fighting done,
他们都想满载金币回家
they want to be home with money in their pockets,
而不是静坐在这种令人消沉的寒冷又潮湿的地方
not sitting in this dismal cold and wet.
优良的战士都没有跑
None of the good men have run.
他们也不会
Nor will they.
他们也不会跟随你到罗马
Nor will they follow you to Rome.
只是时候未到
Not yet.
时间不多了
Time is running out.
我们不能永远等在这里
We cannot wait here forever.
现在是非常时期
This is a very precarious position.
当一月份到来，你任职期限到期时，会发生什么？
What happens in January when your term runs out
难道我们还坐在这里？
and we're still sitting here?
去鼓动战士们打仗是一件微妙的事情，波卡
The business of motivating men to fight is a tricky matter, Posca.
我不期望一个奴隶能够明白其中的奥秘
I would not expect a slave to understand the subtleties.
我相信他们很快就会懂了
I trust an education in these subtleties will begin shortly.
500,000？这是什么？
500,000? What's this?
我提名马克·安东尼竞选护民官
I put Mark Antony up for election as People's Tribune.
所以需要买很多人的选票
There were a lot of votes needed buying.
让马克·安东尼当护民管？
Mark Antony for People's Tribune?
但他
But he is--
尽管说
um...  You may speak.
我明白护民管是一个很神圣的职位
I had understood the Tribune to be a sacred office
拥有否决元老院的权利
with the power of veto over the Senate.
当然，一个非常高贵庄严的职位
So it is. An office of great dignity and seriousness.
可能你是对的
Perhaps you're right.
我们将会派斯特雷波前去确定安东尼行为良好
We shall send Strabo along to make sure Antony behaves himself.
还有多远？
How far now?
还有三个小时的路程
Three hours at pace.
嘿！女孩们，我来了
Ah-hi! Here I come, girls.
我要在城里喝遍所有的酒, 吸遍所有的烟
I'm going to drink all the wine, smoke all the smoke
还要操遍所有的妓女
and fuck every whore in the city.
保持一点尊严，你还不够格
Show some dignity.  You're under the standard.
那好，去跟他说
Well, talk to him.
他不在此列
He's not under the standard.
还有三小时某人就能见到八年没见面的妻子了
Three hours away from a wife he hasn't seen in eight years.
他害怕了，重聚当然是令人高兴的
The man's terrified.  Surely a reunion is a happy event.
谈些其他的  害怕了吧
Talk of something else.  Terrified.
万一她已经掉牙了？ 又或者变得骨瘦如材了？
What if she's lost her teeth? What if she's gotten skinny?
万一她有同别的男人上过床了？
What if she's been letting other men between her legs?
肃静！
Silence!
他们喜欢他，对吗？ 没关系
They love him, eh?  No matter.
我们都是有地位的人
We are all men of substance.
让他们去拥有平民和穷人的爱戴吧
Let them have the love of the plebs and the proles.
这不会持续很久，对吧？
This won't take long, will it?
希望如此，上帝
We can hope, Dominus.
乌瑞纳斯，你可以解散他们了  遵命
vorenus, you may dismiss the men.  Sir.
然后你自己也解散，直到我有任务给你
And then you may dismiss yourself until I send for you.
去找点乐子
Have some fun.
但首先，带着个男孩回
But first, take the boy back to Atia.
拿回你们的报酬
Get your reward, eh?
孩子，告诉你可爱的母亲，我呆会儿会去见她
Boy, tell your lovely mother I will see her later.
让我们把这些办完
Let's get this over with.
Shh!
你，现在马上离开这屋！
You, leave this house this moment.
我不会，屋大维是我名正言顺的妻子
I will not. Octavia is my rightful wife.
你敢违抗恺撒？  恺撒算什么！
You defy Caesar?  A fig for Caesar!
以五复仇女神的名义，如果我不是一位上流社会的女士
By the five furies, if I were not a genteel woman,
我会将你的皮剥掉，然后吊起来挂在门上
I would have you flayed and hung from a bracket at the door!
卡斯特？ 什么事，主人？
Castor?  Domina?
把狗牵来
Fetch the dogs!
傲慢无耻的卑鄙小人！
Insolent wretch!
我告诉你，亲爱的，你已经和那人没有任何关系了
I tell you, my honey, you are well rid of that one.
我恨你
I hate you.
我恨你！我恨你！
I hate you! I hate you!
愚蠢的女孩
Silly girl.
我仅仅是尽全力为她着想，为什么她不明白？
I'm only trying to do my best for her. Why can't she see that?
她还小
She is young.
屋大维主人驾到！ 我亲爱的孩子！
Master Octavian!  Baby boy!
我可怜的小兔崽子！
My poor rabbit!
Oh!
真瘦，旅途很艰辛吧！
So thin. Was it very horrible?
当然，我想都不敢想
Of course it was, I can't even imagine.
我们不要再谈论这个了
We shan't even talk about it.
就把旅途的事完完全全的抛在脑后
We should just put it totally out of our minds.
现在的安全到家就好了
You're back safe at home now.
那些人是谁？
But who are those?
你应该对他们非常好，母亲
You are to be very good to them, Mother.
他们是我特殊的朋友
They are particular friends of mine.
朋友？怎样特殊？
Friends? In what particular?
是他们把被囚禁的我给解救出来的
These are the men that took me from captivity.
首先是枪兵百夫长，卢西尔斯·乌瑞纳斯
First Spear Centurion Lucius Vorenus.
这位是兵团士兵，泰特斯·波罗
And LegionaryTitus Pullo.
我们欢迎你们
So, we embrace you.
你们真叫人敬畏
Good fearsome specimens you are.
我想你们征服那些讨厌的高卢人一定花了很长时间吧
I wonder it took you so long to subdue those odious Gauls.
他们人数非常多，夫人
There was a great many of them, ma'am.
非常多…不错
Great many- very good.
那我们就走了，女士
We'll be away then, sir.
噢，但在你们走之前，你们一定要接受嘉赏
Oh, but you must be rewarded before you go.
卡斯特，把我的钱包拿来  那不必要
Castor, bring me my purse.  That won't be necessary.
不行吗？我没有破坏你们的纪律
Will it not? I don't want to break any regulations--
他们应该留下来吃点东西，母亲
They shall stay and eat, Mother.
当然，面包和肉都在厨房里面
Of course! There shall be bread and meat put out in the kitchen.
我指他们应该和我们一同进餐
I mean, they shall eat with us.
遵命，先生，但我要去找我的妻子
Obliged, sir, but I must go to my wife.
你妻子已经等了八年，可以多等一下
Your wife has waited eight years. She can wait a little longer.
凯撒已经给了他们荣誉坐骑
Caesar has given them honorary horses,
他们还骑着马，拿着军旗回来
and they ride with the standard.
和他们一同进餐是完全可以接受的
It's perfectly acceptable to eat with them.
真是绝妙的主意
Splendid idea.
值得纪念，我们今晚将平等的享受晚餐
It's symbolic. We shall all dine together as equals.
那是什么声音？ 哦，那是你妹妹
What's that?  Oh, it's just your sister.
他没事吧？  妇女之事
Is she all right?  Women's troubles.
哭哭就好了
Nothing a good leeching won't cure.
朱庇特·凡尔格神啊，我们请求你指引并保护这个人
Jupiter Fulgor, we ask you to guide and protect this man,
马克·安东尼，新任护民管
Marcus Antonius, newly elected Tribune of plebs,
以及人民的英雄
champion of the people.
总共杀了多少人？
How many dead altogether?
我不知道，早就数不清了
I don't know. I lost count ages ago.
不过很多
Lots though.
那你喃，卢西尔斯？
And you, Lucius?
309个战士，没有算过有多少平民
309 fighting men. I don't keep count on civilians.
你记得真清楚 战争神殿需要你在
You're very exact.  The war temple requires
供奉时给一个具体的数目
an exact number when you make an offering.
那就意味着要捐很多的酒和羊
That's a lot of wine and goats.
如果你超过100,牧师们会给你些折扣
The priests offer a discount when you pass 100.
牧师！他们多数都是骗子
Priests! Crooks, many of them.
要是我，我就直接同上帝对话
I just talk direct to whatever God I'm doing business with.
作呕的牧师！
Bugger the priests!
很少有人会在意
Too few people can be bothered to do things
以正统的罗马方式来处理事情
the proper, all-Roman way.
我对你的做法表示欣赏，卢西尔斯·乌瑞纳斯是位严格的卡托追随者
I commend you, Lucius.  vorenus is a strict Catonian.
我相信共和国的神灵
I believe in the divinity of the Republic.
如果卡托和我的信仰一样，那我想我应该就是他的追随者
If Cato believes the same, then I suppose I am a Catonian.
但卡托代表的是贵族们的权利
But Cato represents the rights of the nobility.
像你这样的平民肯定希望能发生一些改变
Surely a plebian like yourself would like to see some changes made.
在共和国成立时是什么样，现在就应该是什么样
It should remain as it was at the founding of the Republic.
为什么要改变它？
Why should that change?
因为罗马人民在受苦
Because the Roman people are suffering.
因为奴隶们要做所有的活
Because slaves have taken all the work.
因为贵族们占有了所有的地
Because nobles have taken all the land,
而且遍街都是无家可归和饥饿的人们
and the streets are full of the homeless and the starving.
噢，我还不知道我的孩子是这样的一个煽动者
Well, I had no idea my son was such a firebrand.
贵族们说凯撒是个战犯
The nobles say that Caesar is a war criminal.
他们说他想要踏步走回罗马封自己为王
They say that he wishes to march on Rome and make himself king.
那是亵渎神灵的行为，没人会跟随他的
That is sacrilege. No man of honor would follow him.
恩，那我就失礼了，我会说凯撒应该骑着大象冲回这里
Well, I'm no man of honor then, 'cause I say that Caesar should ride in here
把庞贝、卡托以及其他那些相当国王的人给压扁
with elephants and squash Pompey and Cato and anybody else that wants it.
去他的法律，我就这样认为
Never mind the law. That's what I say.
你这样说是应为你不仅理智有问题
You say that because you govern your reason
还管不住你的嘴
no better than you govern your tongue.
不好意思，是我的错，让大家在喝酒时讨论政治
Forgive me, it's my fault for mixing politics and wine.
还要多些丁鲷吗？或来只榛睡鼠？
More tench? A dormouse perhaps?
谢谢，我够了
Thank you, I won't.
别把我说的放在心上
Don't mind my saying it,
但你们确实不是志同道合的朋友
but you two make unlikely friends.
我们不是朋友关系，我是他的上司
We are not friends. I am his superior officer.
只是从等级划分来看
By virtue of rank, if nothing else.
你已经说够了！
That is enough from you!
请原谅我们鲁莽的行为，夫人
Please forgive our vulgar ways, madam.
我们在你面前显得很不得体
We are not fit for your presence.
没关系，和你们的相处让我感到无比高兴
Not at all. I've enjoyed your company immensely.
非常与众不同
It's been most refreshing.
如果你同意，我们就…
And with your permission, we shall...
离开了
Ieave you.
有空再来玩
Do come and visit us again.
屋大维需要可信赖的朋友
Octavian needs reliable friends.
他可能得依靠你们，我相信
He may depend on you, I trust.
如你所愿，夫人
As you say, madam.
再说一次？  我什么都没说
Say again?  I did not speak.
我走这边
I go this way.
我的家就在那条染色坊街的后面，如果你有什么需要…
My home is behind the street of the cloth dyers, if you--
祝你好运，长官
Go with fortune, sir.
比较干净点的妓院
The cleaner brothels are in the Suburra,
在性爱神殿旁
next to the venereal Temple.
内奥比
Niobe.
你还活着
You're alive.
那是谁的孩子？
What child is that?
回答我
Answer me.
那是谁的孩子？
What child is that?
他是你的孙子
He's your grandson.
说话要有逻辑，妓女
Speak sense, whore.
别动
Wait, now.
你的孙子…你女儿的孩子
Your grandson- the son of your daughter.
我女儿只有…  她都13了，快14了
My daughter is only-  She's 13, near 14.
孩子的父亲是谁？ 一个家禽商人的孩子
A son by who?  Crito, a Drover's boy.
他的名字是卢西尔斯
His name is Lucius.
内奥比，站住
Niobe, stop.
我命令你站住！
I order you to stop!
你们的父亲回来了
Your father's home.
女儿们，他就是你们的父亲
Girls, this is your father.
女儿们，我真高兴你们这么健康漂亮
Daughters, I'm very pleased to find you healthy and good looking.
你们都喜欢跟你们的妈妈在一起吧，恩？
A benefice you favor your mother, eh?
你们的父亲却如此丑陋
Now you see how ugly your father is.
来
Come here.
她不轻信别人，对吧？
She's not simple, is she?
向你们的父亲问好，就像我教你们的那样
Greet your father properly as you've been taught to do.
你的薪水一年前就不再寄过来了
Your pay stopped coming a year ago.
发钱的人说你一定是挂了
The paymaster said you must be dead.
他们说他们从来不会错
They said they don't make mistakes.
该死的家伙们，我有叫他们寄的
Damned fools! I'll have it seen to.
那见到我一定有点吃惊吧？
A bit of a surprise to see me then?
被叫妓女的却有点吃惊
A bit surprised to be called "whore."
我说错了
That was... wrong.
对不起
I am sorry for it.
在大家面前叫我妓女  我说了，对不起
A whore in front of everybody.  I said sorry.
好吃吗？ 下次少放点盐
Is it as you like it?  Less salt next time.
那，你们怎么挣钱的？
So, how did you manage for money?
我妹妹莱蒂和她丈夫帮助了我们
My sister Lyde and her husband helped us out.
你们不必再靠他们的帮助了
Well, you won't need their help anymore.
那些巨大的阴茎是我从
The big phallus is off a Suevi I killed in the Rhinelands--
强壮的野人身上割下来的
a very strong and fierce people.
不错
Nice.
正式的工资都换成奴隶了
My official spoils I've put into slaves.
都在市场
They're at the market.
我净赚了10,000便士
I should clear 10,000 denarii.
这是个好消息
That's good news.
Come with me, sir.
以罗马的恩惠，十二个月亮的名义
By grace of Roma, for twelve moons hence,
在此赋予你护民管的职位
thou art Tribune of Plebs.
终于好了
Abouttime.
我需要喝些酒 当然，长官
I need a drink.  lndeed, sir.
不过可能得先开会
Perhaps after the meeting.
西赛罗
Cicero.
我亲爱的阿提娅，真荣幸
My dear Atia, a pleasure.
原谅我们选择这样不恰当的时间
Forgive us for imposing at such a ludicrous hour.
没关系，我非常喜欢这种神秘的气氛 十分令人激动
Not at all, I adore it. The secrecy, the intrigue- it's most thrilling.
请明白，女人，这是一次机密的会议
Comprehend, woman, this meeting is invisible.
请放心，卡托，我看不见你
Be assured, Cato, I do not see you.
安东尼将军，我们正…
General Antony, we are--
噢，上帝啊，你的美丽真叫人痛苦
Oh God, your beauty is painful.
你是将维纳斯钉死的十字架
You are the crucifix of venus.
让我在你怀中死去吧
Let me die in your arms.
安东尼
'Sist, Antony.
大家晚上好，安东尼将军？
Good evening to you all.  General Antony.
请叫我安东尼护民管
Tribune Antony, if you please.
你现在身处罗马里神圣的地方
You're inside the sacred precincts of Rome,
但你却仍然披着你那件血红的战士披风
but yet you wear the bloody red cloak of a soldier.
Che brutta figura!
我完全没有注意到
It completely fell from my mind.
我向你们致以最深厚的歉意 你们会原谅我吗，我的好友卡托？
I'm most extremely sorry. Will you forgive me, friend Cato?
阿提娅，请把这个拿去烧掉
Atia, please, will you take this and burn it?
没这个必要，是吗？
That's not necessary.  Is it not? Oh, bene.
那我们不要再说废话，直接切入正题吧
Then let's stop all this blathering and get down to business.
你说那些是废话？
Blathering you say?
真是有活力的英雄！
What a congerie of heroes. Such vim!
我感觉自己就像特洛伊的海伦
I feel like Helen of Troy.
你们改到庭院中开会，怎样？
Would you adjourn to the courtyard?
说吧，年轻的马克，你有什么可以告诉我们的？
Speak, young Marcus. What have you to tell us?
我被凯撒任命前来谈判妥协条约
I have been delegated by Caesar to negotiate a compromise.
凯撒希望避免发生流血冲突
Caesar wishes to avoid bloodshed.
他希望别人觉得他是个和情合理的人
He wishes to be seen as a man of reason and probity.
所以，当他在高卢的统制任期结束时
Therefore, when his present term as governor of Gaul has ended,
他愿意接受统制一个军团省份的权利
he is willing to accept command of a single legion province.
优先考虑伊利里亚
Illyria, by preference.
我不明白  统制一个省份
I don't understand.  Command of a province--
这样他才会有合法的豁免权
so he will have legal immunity.
才不至于被你们这些下贱小人给拖到法庭去
So that none of you rascals can go dragging him through the courts.
我们在这里谈论的是凯撒辞职的条件
We're here to discuss the terms of Caesar's resignation.
他可以避免受到起诉
He could have avoided prosecution
只要他肯接受几年时间的流放
by accepting a few years banishment.
为什么而流放？
Banishment for what?
为鼓动专治政权
For fomenting a tyranny.
违法战争，偷窃
Illegal warfare, theft,
谋杀，以及叛国！
murder, treason!
那你会受到什么惩罚，庞贝？
And what shall be your punishment, Pompey,
背弃朋友
for betraying a friend,
抛弃你的人民的利益
for deserting the cause of your people,
还有和这些所谓的贵族结盟
for allying yourself with these so-called noblemen.
你会为这些受到怎样的惩罚喃？ 放肆，狗崽子！
What punishment for you?  lmpudent whelp!
凯撒的任职期还有两周到期
The man's term of office ends in two weeks.
我们说还有六个月  两周！
We say six months.  Two weeks!
他独自一人坐在拉文纳
He sits alone in Ravenna
陪伴他的是一群反叛军团
with one mutinous skeleton of a legion
他居然还敢向我谈条件？！
and he dares to dictate terms to me?!
凯撒不止只有第十三军团
Caesar has many more legions than the 1 3th.
在阿尔卑斯山遥远的另一边
On the far side of the Alps.
冬季不会持续太久
Winter does not last forever.
春天到来，雪便融化
Spring comes, snows melt.
这是在威胁！  请放心，这不是威胁
That's a threat!  I assure you, it is no threat.
雪总会融化
Snows always melt.
如果他得不到他的省
If he does not get a province?
那凯撒就会采取一切必要措施
Caesar will take all measures required
来保护他自己的
to protect both his interests
以及共和国的利益
and those of the Republic.
我真为此感到难过惊讶
I am grieved and surprised.
我还以为这次会是一次合情合理的谈判
I had hoped we would have a rational negotiation.
如果他没有其他要说的了，那我们就走了
If that is his last word, we shall go.
那我们已没什么可谈的了
Then we have no more business.
凯撒只是在虚张声势
Caesar is bluffing.
他只不过装作极度自信
He wishes to appear supremely confident.
很明显他现在已经绝望般的虚弱了，比我们想象的还弱
Evidently he is desperately weak, weaker than we'd thought.
这是他最后一次仗着还有操纵军队的权利企图恐吓我们，让我们做出让步
This is a last ditch attempt to frighten us into making concessions,
虽然它还有军队在虚张声势
while he still has the semblance of an army.
他现在很虚弱，西赛罗，濒临死亡
He's weak, Cicero. Dying.
那现在不正是所有谚语提醒我们该谨慎的时候吗？
Is that not when all the proverbs tell us to be wary?
临死的毒蛇不是咬得最狠吗？
Does not the dying serpent bite deepest?
让我们来玩吧
Let's play.
你从那里来，朋友？  第十三军团
Where are you from, friend?  1 3th.
你最好不要到处宣扬
Better keep that quiet.
这里庞贝的地盘
This is deep Pompeian territory.
我们不都是罗马人吗？
So, we're all Romans, eh?
来啊，女士们，现在起听我的
Come on, ladies, hear me now.
复仇女神和河神，来个五
Furies and River Gods for five.
你会高兴的听到
"You will be pleased to hear
安东尼将军还是如人们所想象的一样傲慢
that General Antony was as blithely arrogant
具有挑衅性
and provocative as one could hope for.
你的谈判立场把庞贝和卡托
And Pompey and Cato were deeply offended
给深深地得罪了
by your negotiating position."
聪明的希腊人保佑我，四点！
Wise Men and Graces on four!
我想希腊人不喜欢你
Those Graces don't like you, I think.
他们在你脸上撒尿  他们在我脸上撒尿？
They piss on your face.  They piss on my face?
他们在我脸上撒尿？！  冷静，兄弟
They piss on my face?!  Calm, brother.
他没有被人好好管教过
Man has an ill way with him.
他输了很多钱，他没有冒犯的意思
He's lost a lot of money. He means no offense...
是吧？ 一点都没有
do you?  None at all.
孪生河神啊，一对二
Twin River Gods over two.
来吧，你这个滑头！
Come on, you mumping cunnies!
一对四
Graces... over four.
现在感觉怎么样，士兵？感觉不错？
How do you feel now, soldier? Feel good?
这人是谁？  快去叫医生！
Who is this man?  Run and get a doctor!
我不希望有人在这屋里死去！
I don't want people dying in my house!
照我说的做，女人！
Do as I say, woman!
Oh!
会有很多浓汁，首先是腐烂的，流完后便会康复
There will be copious pus- first putrid, then wholesome--
可能还有些坏脾气
and mayhap fits of the spleen,
但都是有好处的
but that will be all to the good.
跟着会清除
A purging of the malignancy will follow.
这个是铜币
This is brass.
来
Come.
他什么时候会醒？
When will he wake up?
今天，明天，也许再也不会了
Today, tomorrow, maybe never.
你应该试试去供奉
You might try an offering to Spes.
供奉小白兔常常有用
A white rabbit often works.
我明天会派我的徒弟来检查药剂
I'll send my boy tomorrow to check the dressings.
真是不幸！ 不过是血
What misery!  It's only blood.
洗洗就干净了
It'll wash.
你上哪去？
Where are you going?
我有正事要办
I have business.
正事？什么正事？
Business? What business?
我明白你很焦虑，但我要求你
I understand that you are upset, but I will ask you
不要以这种语气询问我
do not question me in that tone.
语气
Tone.
我爸的公鸡！
My father's cock!
用它的音调怎么样！
How's that for tone?!
50, 50. 55.
55, 55. 60.
60,60…成交！
60, 60- sold!
40. 40, 40, 45.
45, 45, 45. 50.
50. 50, 50. 55.
这是一个好市场，但都是些骨瘦如材的
This is bona stock, but it's all skin and bone, eh?
你想想要个好价钱
You want a good price.
让我们给他们食物吃，给他们增点肥
Let us feed them up, put some fat on them.
只需要几周的小康生活，这些奴隶就会卖得和鹅心一样好
Couple weeks of easy living, and these puppies will sell like duck hearts.
买食物以及储存食物会很贵吗？
Is that expensive, fodder and storage?
不！你会赚回你花在食物上的钱的两倍
No! You'll recoup feed and storage double.
漂亮，对吧？一个真实的表演者
Beautiful, neh? A real showman.
我虽然不是万能的
I am no judge of the sand,
但肯定每个人都能看到
but sure, anyone can see
他是稀有的强壮，充满攻击性
he is rare large and aggressive.
当明天的元老院会议召开
When the Senate meets tomorrow,
西比乌会提议一项对凯撒的终结方案
Scipio will propose an ultimatum be put to Caesar.
我以朋友的身份，希望你明天支持这项方案
I ask you as a friend to support the proposal
并吩咐你的朋友们都来支持
and to enjoin your many friends to do the same.
哦，我并没有多少朋友
Oh, I have not so many friends as all that.
啊，温和派像绵羊一样跟随你
Ah, the moderates follow you like sheep.
你的选票非常关键，最终方案是？
Your vote is critical.  The ultimatum is?
凯撒的任职期一结束
Caesar's term of office is over.
他必须马上解散他的军队
He must immediately disband his men,
辞去他的指挥权，并回来接受审判…
resign his command, and return for trial--
不然的话，他就被当作是元老院和人民的敌人
else be considered an Enemy of the Senate and People of Rome.
但他不会接受的
But he cannot accept that.
那让他身败名裂
Not without dishonor.
一但宣布敌对，他便没有什么可以失去的了…他便会不顾一切的战斗
Once declared hostile, he has nothing to lose- he will fight at any cost.
他会宣布战争！
You are declaring war!
轮不到凯撒决定
Caesar will not have to accept or refuse the terms,
马克·安东尼会直接否决
because Mark Antony will immediately use Tribune's veto.
你的意图是？
But then, what is your purpose?
如果议会反对他
If the Senate votes against him,
恺撒会明白
Caesar will finally understand
他只有孤身一人
that he is alone against all.
除了一张否决票
Of course, anything but an overwhelming vote
让恺撒觉得还有希望
encourages Caesar to think he still has friends and hope.
我不是恺撒的朋友
I am no friend to Caesar, nor any tyrant,
谈我不会否决提议
but I cannot vote for a proposal
那样太没有信仰了
I do not wish to see realized. It would be highly irreligious.
我向朱庇特宣过誓
I have made a vow to Jupiter.
除非明天我能获得全部议员的支持
Unless I get the full backing of the Senate tomorrow,
否则我就把我全部的军团带去西班牙
I and all my legions will sail for Spain
让你们这帮绅士自生自灭
and leave you gentlemen to your own defenses.
这就是他？
This is he? Crito?
他是个好孩子
He's a good boy from good family.
好到让大爷我的
Good enough to seed a child of the vorenii
女儿怀孕？
who fought at Magnesia and Zama?
我不知道，先生 你不知道？！
I don't rightly know, sir.  You don't rightly know?!
你不知道她是我的？
Do you know that this girl is my property?
应该先征得我的同意
That you should have asked my permission
在你们乱搞之前？
before you coupled with her?
对不起  我现在就有杀你的权利
I'm sorry, sir.  I am within my rights to kill you here and now.
爸爸，别，别现在才这样
Papa, please.  Don't you start sniffling.
你被搞之前应该先想到这些
You should have thought of this before you spread your legs.
他们没有要侮辱你
They meant you no disrespect.
他们做的很正常
What they did was only natural.
他们年轻，又相爱着对方
They're young and they love each other.
还是不可容忍
That's no excuse.
他妈妈家里很有钱
His mother's family are well-found in Ostia for many generations,
他爸爸又是很成功的商人
and his father is a successful drover.
他们家就在街对面
They have a house in the southern crossroads.
房间里肯定都是牛粪
A house built from cattle dung no doubt.
那里很干净，一点味道都没有
It's very hygienic, sir. There's no smell.
Huh!
至少家畜商还有钱赚
There's money in droving, at least.
很多钱
Good money, sir.
对于我来说…
I'm on the Capua run mostly--
一星期至少5,000
that's 5,000 head a week sometimes, sir.
不可思议，你什么时候成人？
He cannot be but what he is. When are you a man?
下个月，先生 下个月
Next month, sir.  Next month.
很好，下个月你和我女儿成婚
very well, you may marry my daughter.
和你家人讲准备好嫁妆
Assure your good people that the dowry will be appropriate.
他是个好孩子
He really is a good boy.
你应该感到高兴
You should be pleased.
我女儿失去童贞
My daughter's virginity has been taken
我第一个孙子居然是穷人的孩子
and my first grandson spawned, by an ill-favored prole.
我怎么能高兴？
How can I be pleased?
他让她开心  她真是个傻瓜
He makes her happy.  She's an idiot then.
你真残忍！
What a brute you are!
议员们，听马赛琉斯说
The Senate will hear Metullus Scipio.
说吧！
Speak! Speak!
议员们，我提议
Conscript fathers, I propose a formal motion.
除非盖乌斯·优利乌斯·恺撒
Unless Gaius Julius Caesar
立刻放弃他的指挥权
immediately lays down his command,
解散他的军队然后回罗马
disbands his legions and returns to Rome for trial,
否则议会将宣布他是个公敌
this sacred assembly will declare him a public enemy
罗马人民的敌人！
of the Senate and People of Rome!
在那之后
After which time it will be the duty
那将是所有罗马人的义务
and the obligation of every Roman to do him harm
去杀掉他！
or to kill him if they are able!
议案已经提出了
A motion is proposed.
同意的请表态
Those in favor, make it known.
议案通过
The motion is carried by clear numbers.
安东尼！
Antony!
否决它！
veto the motion!
快否决！
Stand up! veto the motion!
大家安静！大家注意！
I demand the floor! I demand the floor!
听他说！ 我否议案！
Give him the floor!  I veto the motion!
护民管否决议案！
Tribune vetoes the motion!
西比乌的议案反对凯撒
Scipio's motion against Caesar--
立不住脚，对吗？
it doesn't stand, does it?
立的住脚
Stands.
记入年报
Entered in the annals.
护民官反对也不行？
Despite that Tribune raised his veto?
反对没有成立
Not heard, not fully admitted.
分量不够
No weight.
议案通过
The motion stands.
我跟你讲清楚
Let me be clear with you.
我不希望
I do not wish
这样重要的议案
that a motion as important as this
用这种诡计通过
should stand on a mere trick of procedure.
你说诡计？
Trick, you say?
这是宗教的方式
This is a religious matter.
宗教里容不得诡计
There are no tricks in religion.
会议还没正式结束，对吗？
Session was not formally ended, correct?
对，当复会后
Correct.  So, when we reconvene,
还是一样
it will formally be the same session.
护民官安东尼可以否决
Then Tribune Antony may use veto on the motion.
是的
That is so.
天后朱庇特！ 老笨蛋
Juno lnferna! Senile old fool,
为什么你一开始不说？
why didn't you say so to begin with?
马克·安东尼不可以收到任何伤害
Mark Antony must not be harmed or hindered in any way.
但是…无论如何
But-  In any way!
让他能否决这个提议，这一点很重要
It is vitally important that he be allowed to veto the motion.
否则，凯撒就成叛国者了
If he does not, Caesar is declared a traitor.
他就不得不反对我了
Then he has no choice but to oppose me openly,
然后就是战争，马克·安东尼不可以收到任何伤害
which means civil war. Antony must not be harmed!
好消息
Dominus, good news.
议会明天复会
The Senate will reconvene tomorrow.
和上次一样
Formally, it is the same session,
所以你明天还可以否决
so you may yet exercise your veto on the motion.
除非庞贝要阻止我
Hmm. Unless Pompey tries to stop me.
很可能
True, he may very well try.
把人们叫齐
Rally the men together.
乌瑞纳斯
vorenus...
所有的人
all of them.
捉迷藏
& Run and hide&
第十三个来了
&The 13th arecoming&
你的人都死了！
& And your men are all dead! &
我多加了些肉豆
I put extra nutmeg in, as you like it.
嫁给我吧，女神
Oh, marry me, goddess.
像你这样的肥猪？
What, a porcine object like you?
谢天谢地，我已经够惨了
Besides, I am already wed, thanks be to evil spirits.
你错了，他是个好人
You are wrong, friend-wife. He is a good man, your man.
好人？
A good man you say?
这些年来，我每晚都在祈祷
For years and years, I'd lie awake at night
让神把他送回来
and beg all the Gods to send him home.
我听到这场那场战役
I'd hear of this battle or that battle and...
我能清清楚楚地看到他
I'd see him, clear as a glass,
满身血污的躺在地上
Iying dead and bloody in the mud somewhere.
我很孤独
I was lonely.
很孤独
I was so lonely.
八年来我一直哭泣
For eight years I wept.
每天孩子们都问，爸爸什么时候回家？
Every day, the girls asking, "When is Papa coming home?
今天吗？
Is it today? When?"
现在他回来了，我却希望他还在高卢
And now he's home, and I wish he was in Gaul.
他真无情无义
He's a cold, mean brute.
对我们连一句亲切的话都不说
Not one loving word to me or his daughters,
一次都没有
not once since he has been home.
他不会哄女人
He is no skilled hand with the women.
不过这些年我跟着他，他一个女人也没动过
But in all these years I fought with him, he never took a woman.
波罗，他对我说：“我的老朋友
"Pullo," he'd say to me, "Pullo, my old friend,
我有个妻子叫内奥比
I have a wife back home, Niobe is her name
她比所有高卢的女人都珍贵”
and she's worth more to me than all the women of Gaul."
谢谢你的好心话，但我知道你在说谎
I thank you for your kind words, but I know you lie.
他不是你的朋友，他告诉我了
He's no friend of yours. He told me so.
他脾气不好
Why, he has a- an ill temper, him.
什么都说
He'd say anything.
安东尼需要所有人
Antony needs every man.
如果你能走，去阿提娅集合
If you can walk, we rendezvous at the house of Atia.
就这么多了
This is all I have left.
卖掉奴隶后还会有些
There will be more when I sell the slaves.
让孩子们回家，呆在家中知道你认为安全了
Get the girls indoors and stay indoors until you know it's safe.
你不高兴让我很伤心
It saddens me that you are unhappy,
因为我很爱你
because I have a deep affection for you.
我回来后再说吧
When I return, we will talk.
这是件喜事
Well, this is a merry do.
奥克塔维娅，你又有精神了
Octavia, my honey, look alive at least.
可怜的安东尼一定认为自己被忘记了
Poor Antony must think himself dead and swimming in Lethe water.
跟这个可怜的家伙讲讲话
Talk to the poor man, ask him questions.
别人还以为你被德国人养大
One would think she'd been raised by Germans.
安东尼，我妈妈的尖叫让你烦吗？
General Antony, does my mother's screaming irritate you?
你说什么？
Excuse me?
当你们性交的时候
When you and my mother are in coitus,
尖叫声不断
there is a deal of screaming.
我觉得很烦
I find it extremely irritating.
我向你会不会也这样认为呢？
I wondered whether you did also.
也许你很喜欢？
Or perhaps you like it?
证明你的本领
A testament to your skills.
真可恶
So spiteful, and for what?
你自己侮辱自己
You shame only yourself.
正让她说中了
She has you exact.
让他们见识我们的力量
We show our strength.
告诉他们这儿谁说了算
We show them who owns the Forum,
但不要碰他们
but we do not touch them.
不可以碰安东尼
Antony must not be touched!
把他们全杀了  不行
Kill them all, I say.  None of that!
庞贝的命令
Pompey's strict orders.
谁找麻烦就会被钉死
Him who starts trouble will be on a cross at nightfall.
不要流血！
So no blood!
让路！我说让开路！
Make a lane there! Make a lane there, I said!
快点！
Come on, you bastards!
跟我来
Rally to me.
Rally to me!
不要伤人！
No blood!
你有你想要的了，卡托
You have what you wanted, Cato.
凯撒没选择了
Caesar has no choice now.
明年春天，他会翻过阿尔贝斯
Come the spring, he will cross the Alps
带大军向罗马进发
with his legions and march on Rome.
五个死了
Five dead: three from flux, two from fighting.
十个受伤，八个跑了
10 under medics. Eight absent, believed fled.
战斗力量：236人
Sir.  Fighting strength: 236 head.
第七队步兵
Seventh Cohort. 12 dead:
12死
six of flux, six of fighting.
三人受伤
Three on the medics.
三人逃跑
Three absent, believed fled.
战斗力量：242人
Fighting strength: 242.
马克·安东尼在你后面多远？
Soldier, how far behind you is Mark Antony?
不到一小时
No more than an hour, sir.
集合！  是，长官！
Sound assembly!  Sir!
以议会的名义
By order of the Senate,
盖乌斯·优利乌斯·恺撒
Gaius Julius Caesar
成为罗马公敌
is declared an enemy of Rome.
所有公民
All good citizens are bound
有义务去杀掉他
to do him harm if they are able.
我来
I've got him.
这么多年后，庞贝让我吃惊
After all these years, Pompey surprises me.
我曾想主动进攻
I had hoped to provoke some kind of aggression, sure,
但试图在议会谋杀
but to try and kill a Tribune?
护民官？
In the Forum?
The man's found some hard black iron in his soul.
我确定是你那精神错乱的卡托让他做的
I'm sure it was yon demented little worm Cato who put him up to it.
很好，对吗？
It's excellent, this.
接下来？
So, what next?
我们看他还要说什么
Let's see what the men have to say.
别！
Oh, don't do that!
你看上去很好
You look just right as you are.
就像塞莫波莱的里昂纳达
Like Leonidas at Thermopylae.
注意！
Attention!
有什么我可以提到的吗？
Any of your people I can mention?
泰特斯·波罗
Titus Pullo.
砍掉第一个冲向我的人的头
Took the head off the first man that came at me.
士兵们，庞贝和议会
Soldiers, Pompey and the Senate
公开宣布
have formally declared
盖乌斯·优利乌斯·恺撒
that Gaius Julius Caesar
是个公敌
is an enemy of Rome.
不！
No!
他们说我是战犯
They have declared that I am a criminal.
他们公布了，实际上
They have declared, in effect,
你们都是战犯！
that all of you also are criminals!
不！
No!
护民官的否决权无效
The Tribune's veto was not exercised.
护民官马克·安东尼
Peoples Tribune Mark Antony
和13队的50人
and 50 men of the 13th
被1,000庞贝的杂种攻击
were assaulted by 1,000 head of Pompeian scum.
不！
No!
人民的护民官
A Tribune of the plebs
居然在议会门前
assaulted on the steps
被攻击！
of the Senate House!
你们还能想到更严重的亵渎神灵吗？
Can you imagine a more terrible sacrilege?
我们亲爱的共和国正被疯子操纵着
Our beloved Republic is in the hands of madmen.
现在是黑暗时期
This is a dark day,
我站在路中央
and I stand at a fork in the road.
我可以向议会投降
I can abide the law and surrender my arms to the Senate
眼睁睁的看着共和国灭亡
and watch the Republic fall
在暴政和混乱中！
to tyranny and chaos!
或者，我回罗马
Or, I can go home
我可以带着刀剑回去
with my sword in my hand
把那些疯子
and run those maniacs
全都处死！
to the Tarpeian Rock!
Yeah! Yeah!
兵团士兵泰特斯·波罗，请出列！
Legionary Titus Pullo, step forward!
泰特斯·波罗！
Titus Pullo!
当50个勇敢的战士
When 50 brave men of the 13th
与庞贝的1,000人厮杀
fought Pompey's 1,000 in the Forum
试图救护民官时，
and saved the Tribune,
泰特斯·波罗的刀尝到的第一滴血！
it was Legionary Titus Pullo who drew first blood!
500便士！
Here is 500 denarii!
非常感谢
very grateful, sir.
跟我一起吗，泰特斯·波罗？
Are you with me, Titus Pullo?
跟我一起回罗马吗？
Will you come with me to Rome?  Yes.
是的长官！当然！
Yes, sir! Certainly!
泰特斯·波罗跟着我！
Titus Pullo is with me!
你们呢？你们跟着我吗？
And you? Are you with me?!
是的！
Yeah! Yeah!
你醒了
Ah, you're awake.
水？
Water?
我们换地方
We're moving.
Mmm.
听起来向整个军团，哪里？
The whole legion, sounds like. Where to?
一条河
It's a river.
什么河？
What river?
卢比肯河，冷静
This is the Rubicon.  Stay calm.
这是叛国
This is rebellion and treason,
我不是叛国者！
and I am no traitor!
太晚了，我们已经在意大利了
It's too late now. We're across. We're in ltaly.
不管怎样，你已经是造反者了
You're a rebel whether you like it or not.
凯撒，你都作了些什么？
Caesar. Caesar, what have you done?
他没选择
He had no choice, had he?
庞贝要杀马克·安东尼
Pompey did try to kill Mark Antony after all.
你们没资格说
You of all men should not dare make that argument.
什么？ 你知道谁被攻击
How's that?  You know who was being attacked.
什么意思？
I don't know what you mean.
现在没关系了
It doesn't matter now.
我们都死了
We are all dead men any way.
这星期内我们就会被定在十字架上
We'll be hanging from crosses in the Appian Way before the week's out.
不会有事的
We'll be all right.
喝点水，最好渴死
Have some more water.  Better to die of thirst.
别傻了，喝吧！
Don't be foolish. Drink.
凯撒在意大利！
Caesar is in ltaly!
什么
不可能
Caesar is in ltaly!
凯撒在意大利！
听到了吗？ 听到了
Have you heard?  I heard.
会发生什么？
What's going to happen?
战争
War is going to happen.
小猪仔，看谁更馋
Who's my greedy little piglet?
翻译:TLF字幕组